A Guide to the Washington and Lee University School of Law Collection 1849-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Washington and Lee University School of Law Collection 1849-2004
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
003
This collection consists of 1 cubic foot of materials and one oversize folder housed in the map cases.
Administrative Information
Access
Access is unrestricted.
Scope and Content
This collection incorporates very small accessions received in no documentary context. All materials deal with the history of the School of Law at Washington and Lee University and its predecessor institutions, or with alumni of this law school.
In October 2016, the collection was reappraised. Some materials were removed to be placed on other collection or disposed of because they did not have continuing value. Box and folder numbers were assigned and decimal numbers were assigned to each descrete collection within this collection.
Contents List
- Clippings 1934, 1946 (Box-folder 1/1 & Oversize Folder 3)
- The Booklet of the Great War Law Class of Nineteen Seventeen. Washington and Lee University 1920 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Edmund D. Campbell Tributes 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/3)
- A Brief Biogaphy of Rosser Lynn Malone, Jr. and a Photo of Elizabeth Amis Malone 1988 (Box-folder 1/4-5)
- Morton Needs a View or Sherwood v. Walker Revisted 1988, Bound Volume (Box-folder 1/6)
  Law student Shannon Echols hand wrote and illustrated this work in the manner of Dr. Suess.
- Law Student Murdered Cadet -- Only Jury Was Hung, The Rockbridge AdvocateMarch 1995 (Box-folder 1/7 and oversize folder)
- Report Card of H. S. Larrick March 1897 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Autography of Judge Brokenbrough's Law Class of 1859-60 1860 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Lewis Tyree Memorabilia 1913-1915 & n.d. (Box-folder 1/10 & Faculty Photo Series in School of Law Archives)
  These materials, removed from crumbling scrapbook pages, were received in 1996 (accession # 96-2m) from Lewis Tyree, son of the collector of these items. Though Tyree served briefly on the law school faculty, these materials are from his time as a law student at Washington and Lee. There is one folder of printed invitations and programs. All other materials are photographs of students, faculty and events. Seven photos of law faculty members have been separated from this collection and filed in the law school archives faculty photo series.
- In Memoriam John William Eggleston 1886-1976 1976 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Wilbur C. Hall Collection
  - Law Lectures Delivered at Staunton, Virginia 1832 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Letters and Certificates of Award 1916-1945 (Box-folder 1/12 and oversize folder 1)
  - Photographs 1919-1967, 6 photos (Box-folder 1/13 and oversize folder 2)
- John W. Brockenbrough Biographical Information 1865-1998 (Box-folder 1/15)
  This file contains newspaper and magazine articles, and copies of correspondence documenting the life of John W. Brockenbrough, founder of the Lexington Law School. This material came in accession # 98m:002 from Mrs. D. Robert Copeland.
- Introductory Address to the Law Class of Lexington. Delivered in the Franklin Hall; October 31, 1849 by Judge John W. Brockenbrough. 1849, Electrostatic copy. (Box-folder 1/16)
  This copy was provided by the Harvard Law Library via interlibrary loan.
- Memory Book, Washington & Lee University of F. J. Heazel. 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1/17)
  These materials are pages from a scrapbook (accession #99M004) of F. J. Heazel, 1912 graduate of the W&L law school. Eleven leaves of the book remain including the cover. Photos, clippings, and memorabila are affixed to the pages. Some materials had been removed from the pages before the donations. Photos include views of the campus and town of Lexington.
- Funeral of Ethan Allen August 23, 1999 (Box-folder 1/18)
- Death and Funeral of Sydney Lewis 1999 (Box-folder 1/19)
- J. Timothy Philipps Biographical Information 1958-1995 (Box-folder 1/20)
- Class of 1949 Fiftieth Reunion Reminicences April 30, 1999, 1-- 1/2" videotape cassette (Box-folder 1/21)
- Interview with Judge Walter E. Hoffman November 17, 1994, 1 audio cassette and 2 compact disc copies (Box-folder 1/22)
- Investiture Ceremony for William F. Stone, Jr. As The United States Bankruptcy Judge For the Western District Of Virginia July 23, 1999, Program of Events (Box-folder 1/23)
- Diplomas 1867, One original and one photographic reproductions. (Folder 3)
  The original diploma of Oliver P. Evans (2002M:003)was given to the law school by Hayes McClerkin who had purchased it from an a dealer in Charleston, SC.
- F. C. Bryan Reminiscences (2002M:004), August 29, 2002, 15 page letter to archivist John N. Jacob (Box-folder 1/24)
- Samuel J. Graham Photo Collection (2002M:005), 1921-1947, 5 portrait photos. (Oversize Folders 1-5)
  Subjects of photos are U.S. Supreme Court Justices E.D. White, William Howard Taft, Harlan F. Stone, Oliver Wendell Holmes, and Charles E. Hughes. All photos are inscribed to Graham. Provenance is unknown. Photos may have arrived at Washington and Lee University with the Samuel J. Graham Papers now housed in Special Collections, Leyburn Library, Washington and Lee University.
- George D. Shore, Jr. Memorabilia(2003M:001), 1913-1916; 1966, As executor of the estate of her sister, Lila Gayle Hyde Shore, Lucile Hyde Wehman sent the following items formerly belonging to George Decatur Shore, Jr. of the 1916 class of the Washington and Lee University School of Law: 3 editions of The Calyx- 1913, 1914 & 1916; 2 Washington and Lee law diplomas - 1916 Bachelor of Laws and 1969 change to Juris Doctor; 3 photos - unidentified group of young men, c. 1914, & 2 photos from Shore's 50th Washington and Lee class reunion, May 1966; laminated obituary clipping, 1981. The diplomas and c. 1914 photo will be stored in the 003 Washington and Lee University Law School Collection oversize folder in the map case. The Calyxs are stored with the other yearbooks. (Box-folder 1/25 and oversize)
- Washington and Lee University Law Commencement Video Recording(2005M:002), May 8, 2004, CD-R record of commencement exercise. Recorded and donated by John Eisinger. (Box-folder 1/26)
- W.D. Kibler Letters 1896-1898 (Box-folder 1/27)
  Materials are: Letter: John L. Campbell to W. D. Kibler, August 17, 1896. Letter: A. P. Carter to W. D. Kibler, Sept. 10, 1897 Letter: B. R. Kibler to W. D. Kibler, Jan. 29, 1898. These materials, donated by Sharon Hanger Sproul, 41 Woodland Drive, Staunton, VA 24401, came from the estate of her parents, James Brown Hanger, Jr. and Mildred VanPelt Hanger.
- "Law Notes" n.d. (Box-folder 1/28)
  Found item, possibly formerly housed with rare books before their move to archives. Approximately 12" x 8" x .75" printed notebook with printed label "Law Notes Washington and Lee University" on the front cover. Notes appear to be from the 19th century, when compared to dated notes. Notes seem to have been made from reading books, rather than from lectures. There are no identifying markings (excepting "Vol. IV" written on inside cover) indicating who made the notes. There are 319 pages. Notes are made through p. 317, mostly on the right hand side of opened volume.
- Washington and Lee Law Review November 1938 (Box-folder 1/29)
  The 2013-14 editor-in-chief of the Washington and Lee Law Review, Thomas Short, found this volume and gave it to the archives. The creators of the law review, apparently bound reprints of Washington and Lee University Law faculty articles previously published in other law reviews, and the recent cases, notes and book reviews from Kentucky Law Jourrnal, vol. XVII, no. 4, as dummy text when designing the law review format.
- Poetry on the Wings of the Morning: Selected Works of John Charles Thomas, 1967-2011 2011 (Box-folder 1/30)
  This is a copyof retired Virginia Supreme Court Justice John Charles Thomas self published book of his poems, Poetry on the Wings of the Morning. Thomas was Powell Lecturer on April 4, 2016. He gave this book, with its dedication and enclosed note, to Washington and Lee University Dean of the College and English Professor Suzanne Keen. She gave it to the Powell Archives.
- John Randolph Tucker: A Heritage of Law 2011 (Box-folder 1/31)
  This feature was produced by the Public Relations and Media Services of Henrico County Virginia. The subject is Washington and Lee Law alumnus John Randolph Tucker, 1879-1954, grandson of the first dean of Washington and Lee School of Law. Powell Archivist John Jacob is one of the interviewees.
- Calley Court Martial October 23, 1985 (Box-folder 1/32)
  Audio recording of Col. Reid Kennedy lecture on the court martial of Lt. William L. Calley Jr. for his part in the My Lai massacre during the Vietnam War. Stored on 1 compact disc. Recording cataloged in Annie. Donated by R.E. Ruhlman. Kennedy's copyright release form is in "donor" folder of archivist's email account.
- Wider Horizons: Isadore Scott 2006 (Box-folder 1/33)
  Compact disc recording of program honoring Isadore Scott.
- Powell Archives Guest Register Pages 1992-2001 (Box-folder 1/34)
  Pages from Lewis F. Powell Jr. Archives guest register book.
- Law Exams of T.A. Myles 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1/35)
  Five examinations written by T.A. Myles (the questions are not included) while a student at Washington and Lee University School of Law. The subjects are: Insurance, International Law, Corporations, Conveyances and Federal Courts. An undated newspaper clipping with photo of Myles in later life is also included.
- James Stubbs Letters 1861 (Box-folder 1/36)
  Electrostatic copies of two letters (7 leaves) from Washington and Lee law student James Stubbs to his father. Researcher Leslie Bohon made initial inquiry about Stubbs in October 2012. This eventually led to obtaining copies of these letters from the Stubbs Family Papers at Louisiana State University Special Collections. They were both handwritten by Stubbs in Lexington to his father. This was the eve of the Civil War and the letters discuss the tenor of the law school at that time.
- Dualing Oath p.1809 (Box-folder 1/37)
  Handwritten dualing oath. On single page, apparently torn from a book recording marriages and other vital statistics. Found amongst Washington and Lee Law Library rare books formerly owned by Homer Holt.
- Hugo L. Black Letter March 9, 1964 (Box-folder 1/38)
  Typed letter signed by Supreme Court Justice Hugo L. Black. Black is declining invitation of Washington and Lee University School of Law Student Bar Association President, John Dinkel to visit the school. 1 leaf; gift of John Dinkel.
- Joeseph Edward Ulrich Oral History Interview October 29, 1996 (Box-folder 1/39)
  One audio cassette containing interview by Sarah K. Wiant with Joseph E. Ulrich. Oral historian Mame Warren brought the cassette (along with one containing an interview with Roger D. Groot) to the archvies March 21, 2012.
- Veterans Day Tribute to Daniel Clovis Moomaw November 11, 2005 (Box-folder 1/40)
  Program for this event noting the posthumous awarding of the Distinguished Service Cross, Purple Heart, and World War I Victory Medal to Moomaw a Washington and Lee University law student and law professor. A shadow-box (2005A:001) containing the Purple Heart and Victory Medal (with three battle clasps) is stored with artifacts.
- George A. Robinson Law School Class Notes 1877-1878 (Box-folder 1/42-43)
  Accession number 2009M:001. Two bound volumes of notes from law class lectures. First volume contains classes Real Property, Real Property, Partnerships, and Agency. Second Volume includes courses Practice and Pleading, Equity, and Common Carriers. Teachers were Professors John Randolph Tucker and Charles Graves and Judge William McLaughlin.
- Nathan P. Bryan and William J. Bryan Collection 1899-1941 (Box-folder 1/44-47)
  Biographical Information
  Nathan Philemon Bryan (April 23, 1872 - August 8, 1935) was born near Fort Mason, Orange County (now Lake County), Florida, the son of a planter, John Milton Bryan, and his wife, the former Louise Margaret Norton.. He attended the common schools but graduated from Emory College, Oxford, Georgia (now Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia), in 1893. He graduated from the the Washington and Lee University School of Law, Lexington, Virginia, in 1895 and was admitted to the bar that same year. Bryan began practicing law in 1895 in Jacksonville, Florida. He chaired the Board of Control of the Florida State Institutions of Higher Education from 1905 to 1909.
  Bryan became a United States Senator for Florida by appointment on February 22, 1911. Shortly after that, the legislature elected him to that position as a Democrat on March 4, 1911. He served as Senator until March 3, 1917, having been an unsuccessful candidate for renomination in 1916. He chaired the Committee on Claims in the Sixth-third and Sixty-fourth Congresses. He declined the appointment as Governor General of the Philippine Islands by President Woodrow Wilson in 1917.
  Bryan returned to the practice of law and also became a trustee of Emory University. On April 23, 1920, Bryan was nominated by President Woodrow Wilson to the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, to a seat vacated by Robert Lynn Batts. He was confirmed by the United States Senate and received commission the same day. He held this position until his death.
  Nathan's brother, William James Bryan (October 10, 1876 – March 22, 1908), was also born in Orange County Florida. In his short life, he was a politician, attorney, prosecutor and a Democratic U.S. Senator from Florida.
  Bryan attended public schools, graduating from Osceola High School of Kissimmee, Florida. He gained admission to Emory College in Oxford, Georgia (forerunner of today's Emory University) at the age of 16, graduating with a B.A. degree in 1896. Following graduation, Bryan taught school for one year and worked on a plantation for another, all the while studying for law school. Bryan then enrolled in the Washington and Lee University School of Law in Lexington, Virginia, from which he graduated in 1899. He was admitted to the bar that same year and began the practice of law in Jacksonville, Florida.
  In 1903 Bryan married Janet G. Allan. The couple had two children.
  In 1902 Bryan was elected as Duval County solicitor in its Criminal Court of Record. He was re-elected to this office in 1906, remaining in that capacity throughout 1907.
  The day after Christmas 1907, Bryan was appointed to fill a vacancy in the Unites States Senate. About a month after his arrival in the nation's capital, Bryan was stricken with typhoid fever, an illness which caused his premature death on March 22, 1908, at the age of 31. Bryan was buried at Evergreen Cemetery in Jacksonville, Florida.
  (Adapted from Wikipedia visited on 10/27/2016.)
  Accession number 2007M:006. Approximately 2 inches of correspondence (much of of it electrostaticly reproduced) publications, clippings, photos and artifacts produced by or concerning the brothers Nathan P. Bryan and William James Bryan. These materials are arranged in 4 folders and 1 oversize folder, the latter stored in the map cases.
  Materials include: Correspondence and clippings primarily re death of Nathan P. Bryan and dedication of University of Florida Law School building in his honor, 1922, 1935, amd 1941; Excerpts from letters of William James Bryan to Janet Allen Bryan, 1899-1903; Photos and printed campaign literature, c. 1899-1935; Artifacts (brass and glass nameplates), c. 1935; 1895 law diploma from Washington and Lee University; Certificate of Presidential appointment to the 5th Circuit Court of Appeals, 1920, and newspaper article about Judge Bryan Simpson, 1978 (all artifacts but nameplates in oversize folder in map case).